Inventory of the Vic and Barby Ulmer collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Vic and Barby Ulmer collection
1954-2009
1970-1999
95016
Hoover Institution Archives
36 manuscript boxes, 1 cassette box, 1 card file box, 1 videocassette box, 5 oversize folders (15.6 linear feet)
The collection contains photographs, posters, letters, sound and video recordings, pamphlets, bulletins, reports, and other printed matter collected by Vic and Barby Ulmer, founders of Our Developing World. The bulk of the material relates to social, political, and economic conditions in Africa from the 1970s to the 1990s, especially in South Africa, Mozambique, Zimbabwe, and Namibia. Other topics documented in the collection include social and political conditions in Mexico, Central America, and China; international debt; international trade; globalization; and the 1999 World Trade Organization protests in Seattle, also known as the Battle in Seattle.
Ulmer, Vic;; Ulmer, Barbara (Barby)
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1995, with increments received in 1998 and 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom Collection, ARS056, Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound, Stanford University Libraries
South African subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Winifred Armstrong papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Vic and Barby (Barbara) Ulmer are the founders and co-directors of Our Developing World (ODW). Formed in 1982, the non-profit organization strives to raise awareness of the struggles and triumphs occurring in developing countries by creating resources for teachers, hosting events, and leading educational trips to various countries in Central America and Africa.
Vic and Barby Ulmer met while attending the University of California, Berkeley and married in 1954. Barby, a native of San Francisco, worked for many years as an English as a second language instructor. Additionally, she was a leader and active member of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF). She also helped to form the San Jose Peace and Justice Center in 1957 and served as chairman of the organization until 1968. Some of Barby's oral histories discussing her work as an activist have been digitized and can be found in the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom Collection at the Stanford Archive of Recorded Sound.
Vic, originally from Denver, Colorado, was an English teacher at Fremont High School in Sunnyvale, California for many years. He died on May 4th, 2016.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains photographs, posters, letters, sound and video recordings, pamphlets, bulletins, reports, and other printed matter collected by Vic and Barby Ulmer, founders of Our Developing World, a non-profit organization concerned with social, political, and economic issues in developing countries. Much of the material in the collection was collected as teaching material for Our Developing World programs and events.
The bulk of the material relates to conditions in Africa from the 1970s to the 1990s, especially in South Africa, Mozambique, Zimbabwe, and Namibia; however, materials related to Mexico, Central America, and China are also included. Other topics documented in the collection are international debt, international trade, globalization, and the 1999 World Trade Organization protests in Seattle, also known as the Battle in Seattle, which Barby Ulmer participated in.
Arrangement Statement
The material is grouped together by topic according to the Ulmers' original order. The files within each grouping have been organized alphabetically for ease of use, and the original file names have been maintained where possible. Cross references have been added for topics that appear multiple times throughout the collection.
Africa--Politics and government--1960-; Africa--Economic conditions--1960-; Angola--Economic conditions.; Mozambique--Economic conditions.; Zimbabwe--Economic conditions.; South Africa--Economic conditions.; Madagascar--Economic conditions.; Namibia--Economic conditions.; Developing countries--Economic conditions.
- Africa, 1954-2000 (Boxes 1-2)
  Note
  See also: boxes 12, 20, 27-34, and 37-39.
  - General, 1954-1989 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Angola, 1975-1999 (Box-folder 1: 2-4)
  - Senator Alan Cranston letter re Angola, 1986 May 9 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Botswana, 1986 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Ethiopia, 1972-1991 (Box-folder 1: 7-9)
  - Ghana, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Kenya/Tanzania, 1971-1985 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    For additional material on Kenya, see also: boxes 12 and 28. For additional material on Tanzania, see also: boxes 2, 13, 29, and 35-36.
  - Mozambique, 1976-1991 (Box-folder 1: 12-15)
  - Namibia/Angola, 1972-1987 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Our Developing World newsletters, 1996-2000 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    See also: box 28.
  - South Africa, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - South Africa/Zimbabwe, 1973-1989 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Tanzania, 1973-1983 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    See also: boxes 13, 29, and 35-36.
  - Zaire, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Zimbabwe, 1976-1989 (Box-folder 2: 7-11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1981-1999 (Box-folder 2: 12)
- South Africa, 1968-1994 (Boxes 3-6)
  See also: boxes 2, 10-11, 17-19, 26-27, 29-30, 32-35, and 37-39.
  - Accommodation or confrontation, 1977-1984 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Action on Africa, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Apartheid articles, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Apartheid practices, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Articles, 1976-1985 (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - Bantustans, 1976 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Centre Office de la Recherche Scientifique et Technique d'Outre-Mer de Tananarive, 1968-1975
    - Works published from 1968-1969, 1968-1971 (Box-folder 3: 8)
    - Works published from 1970-1971, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - Works published from 1971-1972, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Works published from 1972-1973, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - "Conference on Economic Alternatives,", 1973 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Economy, 1985 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Education, 1974-1983 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Elections, 1984 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Foreign policy, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Health (1984 Carnegie Report) (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Human rights, 1974 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Ngkane, Barney, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Non-violence and Southern Africa, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Opposition: Black South Africa, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Opposition: White South Africa, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - "South African Bishops' Declaration of Commitment to Racial Justice,", 1976-1979, 1984 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - South African prisons - detention, suicides, 1967-1977 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - South African speakers, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Soweto student protests, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Squatters and housing, 1975-1984 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Transkei, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - U.S. arms sales, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - U.S. business in Southern Africa, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - U.S. policy, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - U.S. policy and needs, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Vorster, [John], 1976-1981 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1977-1994 (Box-folder 5: 16, Box-folder 6: 1-5)
- Human rights/trade, 1994-2006 (Box 7)
  - Fair trade materials, 1996-2006 (Box-folder 7: 1-4)
  - Free trade materials, 1999-2004 (Box-folder 7: 5-7)
  - Human rights materials, 1994-2005 (Box-folder 7: 8)
- Namibia/Zimbabwe, 1961-2003, undated (Boxes 8-9)
  - Namibia, 1961-2003
    See also: boxes 2, 28, 34-35, and 37.
    - General, 1986-2003 (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
    - "Bushmen, Africa's Vanishing Nomads,", 1961-1968 (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - Education, 1988-1993 (Box-folder 8: 5-6)
    - Elections, 1999 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Health aids, 1986 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Human rights, 1993 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - Literary campaign/disabled persons, 1990 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - Maps/guides, 1999-2002 (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - Physical/science/metric, 1994 (Box-folder 8: 12)
    - Resources, 1990 (Box-folder 8: 13)
    - Self-help housing, 1992 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Zimbabwe, 1981-2000, undated
    See also: boxes 2, 31-32, 34, 36, and 38.
    - Arts/crafts, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 8: 15)
    - Development projects, 1986-2000 (Box-folder 8: 16)
    - Disabled persons, 1984 (Box-folder 8: 17)
    - Economy, 1993 (Box-folder 8: 18)
    - Education, 1988 (Box-folder 8: 19)
    - Facts/tourism, 1990 (Box-folder 8: 20)
    - Health, 1994 (Box-folder 8: 21)
    - History, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 8: 22)
    - Land ownership, 1991 (Box-folder 8: 23)
    - Magazines, 1984 (Box-folder 9: 1)
    - Maps/tourism, 1983 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - National parks conservation, 1989 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - Racial disharmony, 1993 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Visuals, undated (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Women, 1995 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 9: 7)
- West Africa, 1971-2003, undated (Box 9)
  - Ghana, 1975-1991 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Mali, 1975-2003 (Box-folder 9: 9-11)
  - Niger, 1971 (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - Nigeria, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Senegal, undated (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Western Sahara, 1979 (Box-folder 9: 15)
- South Africa, 1964-2007 (Boxes 10-11)
  See also: boxes 2-6, 17-19, 26-27, 29-30, 32-35, and 37-39.
  - Apartheid and AIDS rap lyrics, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Child labor, 1964-2007 (Box-folder 10: 2-3)
  - Coffee: child slavery, 2001 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - Court justices, 1996 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Development projects and change, 1983-1995 (Box-folder 10: 6)
  - Economics, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 10: 7)
  - Elections, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Fair trade chocolate, 2002 (Box-folder 10: 9)
  - Human/children's rights, 1992-1999 (Box-folder 10: 10)
  - Labor and economy, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 10: 11)
  - Land/ref., 1990-1991 (Box-folder 10: 12)
  - Lesson plans and teaching material, 1975-2004, undated
    - Africa: Unit 4-8th, 1975-1983 (Box-folder 10: 13)
    - Bigelow: handouts and worksheets, undated (Box-folder 10: 14-15)
    - Grades 5-12, 1990-2004 (Box-folder 10: 16)
    - Intro activity, undated (Box-folder 10: 17)
    - Junior high school lessons, 1994 (Box-folder 10: 18)
    - Lessons - beginning, 1990 (Box-folder 10: 19)
    - Role playing negotiations, 1991 (Box-folder 10: 20)
    - Role plays and fact sheet, 1985-1992 (Box-folder 10: 21)
  - Math/games/culture, 1986 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - National Council of Social Service (NCSS)/Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC), 1998 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - "Now Is the Time" poem/change, 1991 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Peoples, 1977-1996 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Racism, 1988, 1996, 1999 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Readings, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Reconciliation, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Resources, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - Role of humor, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - South African fairy tale, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - South African perspectives, 1973 (Box-folder 11: 11)
  - Video notes and related material, 1982-1999, undated
    See also: box 39.
    - Children of Apartheid, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 11: 12)
    - Cry for Reason, 1988-1999 (Box-folder 11: 13)
    - Mandela, undated (Box-folder 11: 14)
    - Voices from South Africa, undated (Box-folder 11: 15)
    - Witness to Apartheid, 1988 (Box-folder 11: 16)
  - Violence: Safer Schools Project, undated (Box-folder 11: 17)
  - Visuals, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 11: 18-19)
  - Women/children of abuse, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 11: 20)
  - Zulu fairy tale, 1992 (Box-folder 11: 21)
- Miscellaneous, 2001-2006, undated (Box-folder 11: 22)
  Scope and Contents note
  Books and clippings related to women and children in South Africa and Latin American countries. Also included are visuals used in Our Developing World's Central America Teaching Kit.
- East Africa, 1979-1993 (Box 12)
  - Nationalism/post-colonialism, 1993 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Kenya, 1979-1990 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    See also: boxes 1 and 28.
- Central Africa, 1985-2007 (Box 12)
  - Burundi, 1996 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Congo, 2002 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Peace Corps/Zaire, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 5)
  - Uganda, 2007 (Box-folder 12: 6)
- Africa, 1968-2002, undated (Box 12)
  See also: boxes 1-2, 20, 27-34, 37, and 39.
  - General, 1988-1989, 2001 (Box-folder 12: 7-8)
  - African press: analyzing unit, 1985 (Box-folder 12: 9)
    Contains material related to a lesson plan on how to analyze African media and press.
  - Agricultural development/alternative energy, 2002 (Box-folder 12: 10)
  - AIDS epidemic, 2001 (Box-folder 12: 11)
  - Art/sculpture, 1989 (Box-folder 12: 12)
  - Bibliographies, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 12: 13-14)
  - Colonialism, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Deserts, 1968 (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - Healthcare, 1975 (Box-folder 12: 17)
  - Lessons and maps, 1989 (Box-folder 12: 18)
  - Music and dance, undated (Box-folder 12: 19)
  - Recipes, undated (Box-folder 12: 20)
  - Resource centers, 1979 (Box-folder 12: 21)
  - Sahel/cattle, undated (Box-folder 12: 22)
  - Visuals, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 12: 23)
  - Wildlife, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 12: 24)
  - Women, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 12: 25)
- North Africa, 1957, 1976, 1984 (Box 13)
  - Egypt, 1984 (Box-folder 13: 1)
  - "From Papyrus to Paperback," radio transcript, 1957 November 3 (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Morocco, 1976 (Box-folder 13: 3)
- East Africa, 1966-2002, undated (Boxes 13-14)
  - Ethiopia, 1987-2002 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
  - Sudan, undated (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Tanzania, 1966-2001, undated
    See also: boxes 1-2, 29, and 35-36.
    - Art/teaching art, 1966 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - Course outlines, 1978 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - Dar es Salaam map, undated (Box-folder 13: 9)
    - Education, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 13: 10)
    - Family planning/"child spacing,", 1979 (Box-folder 13: 11)
    - Game parks, 1980-2001 (Box-folder 13: 12-13)
    - Health care, undated (Box-folder 13: 14)
  - Zambia, 1977 (Box-folder 14: 1)
- Southern Africa, 1981-2007, undated (Boxes 14-15)
  - Angola, 1981-2004 (Box-folder 14: 2-3)
  - Co-ops, 1989 (Box-folder 14: 4)
  - Madagascar, 1998 (Box-folder 14: 5)
  - Mozambique, 1981-2007, undated
    See also: boxes 1, 34-35, and 37.
    - '90s - change, 1990 (Box-folder 14: 6)
    - AIDS, undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
    - Current, 1991-2007 (Box-folder 14: 8)
    - Education, 1988 (Box-folder 14: 9)
    - Elections, 1995 (Box-folder 14: 10)
    - Literacy, 1981 (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - Maps, 1986 (Box-folder 14: 12)
    - Music, 1981 (Box-folder 14: 13)
    - Notebooks, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 14: 14)
    - Overview, 2002 (Box-folder 14: 15)
    - Resource kit, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 14: 16)
    - Resources, 1981-2000 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - South African (SA) independence, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 15: 2)
    - Story and slide narration, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 15: 3)
    - Update, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 15: 4)
    - Visuals, 1983 (Box-folder 15: 5)
    - Women, 1984-1996 (Box-folder 15: 6)
    - Women/visuals, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 15: 7)
  - Southern and central Africa maps, 1990 (Box-folder 15: 8)
  - Swaziland, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 15: 9-10)
- International debt crisis, 1980-2006 (Boxes 15-17)
  - General, 1984-2006 (Box-folder 15: 11-15)
  - Africa and international debt, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 15: 16)
  - Banking, 1984 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Bibliography, undated (Box-folder 16: 2)
  - Cartoons, 1985 (Box-folder 16: 3)
  - Commodities, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 16: 4)
  - Debt and environment, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 16: 5)
  - Debt for equity, 1988 (Box-folder 16: 6)
  - Economics, 1993 (Box-folder 16: 7)
  - Effect on U.S., 1986 (Box-folder 16: 8)
  - Farm [policy], 1984-1987 (Box-folder 16: 9)
  - Growth, 1987 (Box-folder 16: 10)
  - Hunger, 1977-1986 (Box-folder 16: 11)
  - Hunger and militarism, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 16: 12)
  - International debt vs. rights of indigenous, 1982 (Box-folder 16: 13)
  - International Monetary Fund (IMF)/World Bank, 1980-1987, 1991-2006 (Box-folder 16: 14-17)
  - Jubilee 2000, 1998-2001 (Box-folder 16: 18-19)
  - Latin America, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - Mexico, 1987 (Box-folder 17: 2)
  - Misconceptions, 1986 (Box-folder 17: 3)
  - Morality, 1986-2005 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - Networking and resource persons, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 17: 5)
  - Self-reliance, 1985 (Box-folder 17: 6)
  - Solidarity: U.S./Brazil, 1986-1999 (Box-folder 17: 7)
  - Solutions, 1984-1990, 2000 (Box-folder 17: 8)
  - Statistics, 1986 (Box-folder 17: 9)
  - U.S. black farmers, 1985 (Box-folder 17: 10)
  - Women's alternatives, 1986 (Box-folder 17: 11)
- South Africa, 1986-2004, undated (Boxes 17-19)
  See also: boxes 2-6, 10-11, 26-27, 29-30, 32-35, and 37-39.
  - Ecumenical Monitoring Programme for South Africa (EMPSA) and elections, 1994 (Box-folder 17: 12)
  - EMPSA reports, 1994 (Box-folder 17: 13)
  - Elections, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 17: 14)
  - Foreign policy, 1996 (Box-folder 17: 15)
  - Handouts, 1994 (Box-folder 17: 16)
  - Health, 1991-2000 (Box-folder 17: 17)
  - Holocaust exhibit (Cape Town), undated (Box-folder 17: 18)
  - Housing, 1996 (Box-folder 17: 19)
  - Human rights, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - Indian Ocean: Durban - Cape Town, 2002 (Box-folder 18: 2)
  - Indians and "coloreds,", 1994-1999 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - Inkatha, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - Investment, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Land, 1994-1999 (Box-folder 18: 6)
  - Literacy and numeracy, 1996 (Box-folder 18: 7)
  - Lobolo, undated (Box-folder 18: 8)
  - Mandela, Nelson, 1987-1999 (Box-folder 18: 9)
    See also: boxes 37 and 39.
  - Multicultural and diversity, 1996-2002 (Box-folder 18: 10)
  - Music, 1986 (Box-folder 18: 11)
  - National Party, 1993, 1997 (Box-folder 18: 12)
  - New government, 1994 (Box-folder 18: 13)
  - New Partnership for Africa's Development (NEPAD), 2002 (Box-folder 18: 14)
  - Newspapers, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 18: 15)
  - Notebook, 1996 (Box-folder 18: 16)
  - Olympics, 2004 (Box-folder 18: 17)
  - Photographs, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 18: 18)
    Includes images taken in Johannesburg and Natal.
  - Police, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 18: 19)
  - Ramphele, Mamphela, 1996 (Box-folder 18: 20)
  - Resources, 1987 (Box-folder 18: 21)
  - Rock art paintings, 2002 (Box-folder 18: 22)
  - Sister city, 1995 (Box-folder 18: 23)
  - Sisulu, Walter, 2004 (Box-folder 18: 24)
  - Street children, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 18: 25)
  - South African Council of Churches (SACC), 2002 (Box-folder 18: 26)
  - Tourism, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 19: 1)
  - Trade unions, 1995 (Box-folder 19: 2)
  - Truth and Reconciliation Commission (TRC), 1995-2002 (Box-folder 19: 3-6)
  - TV, 1999 (Box-folder 19: 7)
  - U.S. business investments, 1998 (Box-folder 19: 8)
  - Women, 1994-2002, undated (Box-folder 19: 9-10)
  - Women and the land, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 19: 11)
  - Workers, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 19: 12)
  - Youth, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 19: 13)
- Africa, 1989-2006, undated (Box 20)
  See also: boxes 1-2, 12, 27-34, 37, and 39.
  - Africa Initiative, 2002-2005 (Box-folder 20: 1)
  - Africa Network, 1989-2002 (Box-folder 20: 2)
  - African National Conference (ANC), 1994-2002 (Box-folder 20: 3)
  - Amakhosi - chiefs, 1995 (Box-folder 20: 4)
  - Anti-apartheid, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 20: 5)
  - Arms, 1994, 2002 (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - Arts, 1993-1996 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Beacon, 2006 (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - Biehl, Amy, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - Building democracy, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 20: 10)
  - Business code of conduct, 1994 (Box-folder 20: 11)
  - Census, 1996 (Box-folder 20: 12)
  - Conflict resolution, undated (Box-folder 20: 13)
  - Crime, 1996 (Box-folder 20: 14)
  - Congress of South African Trade Unions (COSATU), 1995-1996 (Box-folder 20: 15)
  - Cradle of Mankind [Cradle of Humankind], undated (Box-folder 20: 16)
  - Debt, 1998-2003 (Box-folder 20: 17-18)
  - Defense, 1999 (Box-folder 20: 19)
  - Development in townships, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 20: 20)
  - Development projects, undated (Box-folder 20: 21)
  - Diamonds, 2001 (Box-folder 20: 22)
  - Durban: Cato Manor, undated (Box-folder 20: 23)
  - Economy, 1994-2002 (Box-folder 20: 24)
  - Education, 1994-2001 (Box-folder 20: 25)
  - U.S. foreign policy, 1997 (Box-folder 20: 26)
  - U.S. policies, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 20: 27)
- World Trade Organization (WTO) and globalization, 1997-2006, undated (Boxes 21-23)
  See also: box 38.
  - Alternatives to IMF [International Monetary Fund] World Bank and WTO, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 21: 1-2)
  - Cartoons, undated (Box-folder 21: 3)
  - Globalization, 2000-2005
    - Central America Free Trade Agreement (CAFTA), 2002-2005 (Box-folder 21: 4)
    - Empire/imperialism, 2003 (Box-folder 21: 5)
    - Factory simulation, 2005 (Box-folder 21: 6)
    - Free Trade Area of the Americas (FTAA), 2000-2003 (Box-folder 21: 7-8)
    - Global awareness teaching activities, 2005 (Box-folder 21: 9)
    - Global education, 2001-2002 (Box-folder 22: 1)
    - NAFTA and globalization, 2001 (Box-folder 22: 2)
    - Plan Puebla Panama, 2002 (Box-folder 22: 3)
  - The Grassroots Guide to the IMF and World Bank, circa 2002 (Box-folder 22: 4)
  - [International] Right to Know, undated (Box-folder 22: 5)
  - Porto Alegre, 2002 (Box-folder 22: 6)
  - Student anti-global corporations movement, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 22: 7)
  - World Trade Organization (WTO), 1998-2006 (Box-folder 22: 8-11)
  - "WTO for Beginners,", 2000 (Box-folder 22: 12)
  - WTO lesson, 1999 (Box-folder 22: 13)
  - WTO Seattle, 1999-2000
    Also known as the Battle of Seattle or the Battle in Seattle.
    - General, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - Clippings, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 23: 2-18)
    - Photographs, 1999 (Box-folder 23: 19)
      Includes images of Barby Ulmer taken in downtown Seattle during the protests.
    - World Trade Observer, 1999 (Box-folder 23: 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 23: 21)
  - Miscellaneous, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 23: 22)
- Trade/Mexico, 1992-2006, undated (Box 24)
  - Free trade, 1992-2002 (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - Maquiladoras, 1996 (Box-folder 24: 2)
  - Mexico/NAFTA/U.S. military interdependence, 2001-2006 (Box-folder 24: 3)
  - Mexico and U.S., undated (Box-folder 24: 4)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1993-2003 (Box-folder 24: 5)
  - Sweatshops, 1997-2004 (Box-folder 24: 6-7)
- Nicaragua, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 24: 8)
- Sustainability, 1997-2007, undated (Boxes 24-26)
  - Agriculture, 1998-2006, undated
    - Clippings, 2002 (Box-folder 24: 9)
    - Genetically modified foods, 1998-2004, undated (Box-folder 24: 10-11)
    - Pesticides, 2003 (Box-folder 24: 12)
    - Promised Land: Competing Visions of Agrarian Reform, 2006 (Box-folder 24: 13)
    - Sustainable agriculture, 2004 (Box-folder 24: 14)
  - Camels and development, 2006 (Box-folder 24: 15)
  - Earth Island Journal, 2000 (Box-folder 24: 16)
  - Economic justice, 2002 (Box-folder 24: 17)
  - Energy from the ocean, undated (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - Environmental degradation, 2005 (Box-folder 25: 2)
  - Fish and ocean, 2002 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - Forest preservation, 2001 (Box-folder 25: 4)
  - Global warming, 1997-2007 (Box-folder 25: 5-6)